[music]
>> celebrating Consortium News's 30th
birthday. I'm Joe Lauria, the
editor-in-chief of Consortium News.
With me is Kathy Vogan, our executive
producer in Sydney, and Elizabeth Voss
in Arkansas.
30 years ago today, on November 15,
1995, former Associated Press
investigative reporter Robert Parry
founded a website he initially called
the Consortium and later Consortium
News.
Parry started online with two of his
heroes had done on paper. And those
heroes were the muckraking independent
journalists I.F. Stone and George
Seldes.
Bypassing corporate media, Bob started
the model for online journalism that
blazed the trail for an explosion of
independent media today that
collectively is seriously challenging
the dominance of mainstream media.
Consortium News gave the public two
crucial things the mainstream didn't
and continues to give. One, it gives
politically damaging stories to the
establishment that corporate media
suppresses
and also angles the mainstream media
ignores that provide essential
historical context that corporate media
conveniently omits.
Here is how Consortium News began in Bob
Parry's own words.
In 1995, after more than two decades in
the mainstream news media in AP,
Newsweek and PBS, I founded Consortium
News as a home for the serious
journalism that no longer had a place in
an American news business that had lost
its way.
At the time, I was the lead journalist
on what had become known as the
Iran-Contra scandal, and I had watched
firsthand as senior news executives
chose to squelch that inquiry,
apparently out of fear that it would
cause another impeachment crisis around
another Republican president, Ronald
Reagan.
Such a possibility was deemed not good
for the country, a view held both inside
Congress and in the boardrooms of the
elite national news media. But I refused
to accept the judgment. I continued to
pursue the many loose ends of the
scandal, from evidence of drug
trafficking by Reagan's beloved
Nicaraguan contras to suspicions that
the arms-for-hostages deals with Iran
started much earlier, possibly even
during the 1980 presidential campaign.
The era of Watergate had come full
circle. Instead of exposing crimes and
cover-ups, the Washington press corp
corp's job had changed into harassing
and mocking serious investigators, the
likes of
uh Iran-Contra special prosecutor
Lawrence Walsh, who stayed on the trail.
The Washington news media had drifted
into a culture of careerism, with the
top jobs paid well into the six and
seven figures. Your hairstyle and glib
presentation on TV were far more
important than the quality of your
reporting.
And the most important thing was to
avoid the wrath of right-wing attack
groups who would controversialize you.
By the mid-90s, it had become clear to
me that there was no feasible way to do
the work that had to be done within the
confines of mainstream media. The
pressures on everyone had grown too
intense. No matter how solid the
reporting, many issues were simply
off-limits, particularly scandals that
reflected badly on the admired duo of
Ronald Reagan and George H. W. Bush.
Bob Parry continues, "Even when I
obtained highly classified government
documents in 1994 and 1995 shedding
light on how US policies towards Iraq
and Iran had evolved at the start of the
Reagan-Bush era, this information could
find no home, even in the liberal
outliers of the mainstream media.
So on the advice of my oldest son, Sam,
who told me about this strange new
phenomenon called the internet, I
started this website in fall 1995.
Besides seeing Consortium News as a
place for serious journalism, I also
envisioned it as a refuge for quality
journalists who faced the same
frustrations that I did. Close quote."
And that's how Consortium News was born,
as a consortium for mainstream
journalists who, like Bob, had had their
stories suppressed.
Some of the biggest stories that Bob
covered we will look at now. One of them
was managing public perception, or aka
propaganda. He Bob uncovered important
details on the CIA in the Reagan
administration working to manage
America's perceptions, Americans'
perceptions, away from the critical
thinking of the 1970s.
A big story, the first really big story
that Bob worked on
at Consortium News of worldwide
importance was the Iraq 2003 invasion.
There was virtually no one in the
mainstream media who questioned the
fevered march towards an unprovoked
invasion of Iraq in 2003. I, Joe Lauria,
was covering the UN for a Canadian
newspaper chain that published a
Montreal Gazette and the Ottawa Citizen
at the time, and I was fired on the day
of the invasion for having questioned
the rationale and the legality of the
invasion in my reporting from UN
headquarters in New York.
Chris Hedges, today a member of
Consortium News board, had to leave the
New York Times after speech he gave
opposing the invasion.
That's what it was like in the
mainstream media at that time.
But over at Consortium News, there was
open and repeated questioning of the
Bush administration's motive and cover
story for invading a country that posed
no danger to the United States.
It was shortly after the invasion that
the Veterans Intelligence Professionals
for Sanity, or VIPS,
uh one of whose co-founders is with us
tonight, was formed to follow up on the
criminality of the invasion and then on
many other issues.
Another major story covered by
Consortium News was has been Ukraine.
Bob was a real investigative reporter, a
term that is very loosely appropriated
today by many beginners in this trade.
That meant that he spent months on a
single story in the days when news
organizations spent real money on that
sort of thing. He also knew what it
meant to be politically neutral. While
he attacked the right from 1995, in
2014, he began to take on the
nonpartisanship that characterizes
Consortium News by contacting by
attacking the Democrats, too. It began
in earnest with his and other Consortium
News writers' questioning of the events
in Kiev in February of 2014. Bob's
reporting led the way to establishing
that a US-backed coup took place then, a
fact that mainstream media still denies,
and he explained the civil war that the
US-backed coup government unleashed on
Donbas, leading to Russia's intervention
into the civil war in 2022.
Of course, this led to baseless
accusations that Bob and Consortium News
were in the play in the pay of the
Kremlin, blah blah blah, vicious smears
that persist until today. That's what
happens when your factual reporting
exposes an empire's agenda.
In 2016, Consortium News was among the
very first news organizations, one of
our guests was the first, to expose the
so-called Russiagate scandal as a
fraudulent attempt to dress up
Democratic Party opposition research as
serious intelligence, which led to
powerful US intelligence agencies
interfering in US domestic politics at
the national level, a very serious
matter indeed.
Along with Bob, CN writers like Ray
McGovern, also a guest tonight, Gareth
Porter, and myself delved deeper into
the deception of the scandal, leading to
even harsher accusations of us being
Kremlin stooges, which led to
disagreements with family and friends in
a fiasco that will not die, even though
it has been definitively debunked.
Since Bob Parry left, and
I will speak about some of the things
we've done since Bob Parry left. My
first my very first article in 2011 in
Consortium News came about as I was
working for the Wall Street Journal,
uh and I who continuously suppressed
stories that I was working on. One of
them was about Palestine becoming an
observer state at the UN.
I sent one of these spiked articles to
Bob, and he published it.
That day I became part of his consortium
of mainstream journalists who found a
way to get out his unapproved work.
Since I became the editor-in-chief of
Consortium News following Bob's very
untimely death in 2018, January of 2018,
Consortium News continued Bob's work on
Russiagate, Ukraine, and the Middle
East, especially on Gaza in the past few
years.
Consortium News has also distinguished
itself in its coverage of the
persecution of journalist Julian
Assange, which Bob Parry wrote about in
2010, December, at the very beginning.
He figured out that story, incidentally.
The persecution of Assange by the US and
British governments.
Naturally, that made us even more
enemies of those pursuing their own and
not the public's interests.
In the summer of 2019,
Consortium News began its webcast
program, the one you're watching now, CN
Live, and I, Kathy Vogan, am the
executive producer. Bob Parry always
wanted to do more video, as he saw that
that was the future in independent
online journalism. Just going to turn
this on.
Okay, he had made a very rudimentary
start. At the beginning of 2018,
a Consortium News videos were only
watched in five countries. When CN Live
started, it was seen in 18 countries.
And by 2020, it was up to 48 countries.
Today, it's 163
countries. CN Live made its mark,
especially in the coverage of the
Assange case, but also on Gaza, Ukraine,
the Ep- stein case, and many more
topics.
Thank you, Kathy.
Most people are motivated by
self-interest, but not everyone. Even
though those who are motivated by
self-interest think every thinks that
everyone else is.
Taking Russia or China or Iran's or
Palestinian's point of view into account
is death for the career of a Western
journalist. So, why would Bob Parry and
the many contributors to Consortium News
do that?
Except that they are motivated by
something higher than self-interest.
Before we begin our discussion, I want
to share these words by the late and
truly great John Pilger
um which he said on the 25th anniversary
of Consortium News. Quote, Consortium
News was started 25 years ago by the
late Robert Parry, one of America's
finest journalists. It is the newspaper
you can no longer buy at the newsstand.
An oasis of real journalism which now
needs your support urgently.
So, we do ask you in the course of this
show and afterward to go to our website,
consortiumnews.com, and there's a red
button that says donate on that. Please
press that and help us out during our
30th anniversary fall fund drive.
Our guests tonight are former CIA
analyst Ray McGovern and John Kiriakou
to discuss how they became dissidents
and transitioned to journalism. And then
we have two veteran highly accomplished
ex-mainstream media journalists
Mary Kostakidis and then Patrick
Lawrence to discuss the state of media
today and increasingly influential role
of independent media in challenging the
mainstream dominance.
First guest is Ray McGovern, probably
the second most important figure in the
history of Consortium News, Ray.
On uh December 28, 2011, Bob Parry
wrote, quote, "To my great satisfaction,
we also began developing what might be
regarded as unlikely relationships, we
being Consortium News, unlikely
relationships with former CIA analysts
such as Ray McGovern, Peter Dickson,
Melvin Goodman, and Elizabeth Murray.
Though these CIA folks had been trained
not to talk to journalists like me,
it turned out they also were looking for
places to impart their important
knowledge. I found that our experiences
had run on parallel tracks. In the
1980s, as the Washington press corps was
facing intense pressure to tow the
Reagan-Bush line, the CIA analysts were
experiencing the same thing inside their
offices at Langley.
It became clear to me that the right's
central strategy of that era had been to
seize control the information flows out
of Washington. To do so required
transforming both CIA analysts and
Washington journalists into
propagandists.
The crowning achievement of that project
had been the
towering CIA analysts and fawning
journalism that had been used to whip up
popular support for George W. Bush's
invasion of Iraq in 2003. And that is
where I fear we still stand, Bob Parry
wrote in 2011, stuck in a dangerous
swamp of disinformation, spin, and lies.
And I dare say we're still in that
swamp. Ray McGovern, thanks for joining
us. Ray, can you please
for our audience, explain what you did
at the CIA concisely,
what made you a dissident, and how you
transitioned into journalism with the
assistance of Robert Parry?
Take it away, Ray.
Well, thanks, Joe. Uh first let me add
an addition here.
On Russiagate, uh the very first person
to release the whole shamir and analyze
it exactly right was another fellow
called Patrick Lawrence. I think he's
right there. There he is, Patrick.
And if you want to see something really
artful,
you could see what Patrick did on Salon
the day that uh Hillary Clinton's folks
decided this is what they're going to
do. The very day Democratic National
Convention. So, I you know, I really
feel that Patrick was even a couple of
weeks before the rest of us.
Anyhow, uh I was an analyst at CIA in
current intelligence. That meant that I
was a sort of a journalist. I had access
to other sensitive sources, of course.
And I had to make judgments based on
fragmentary
uh not not the whole picture. That was a
little different from journalism. And
when Bob Parry asked me to join
Consortium News, it was a delight
because I knew what Bob had done in his
work on
on Central America in particular.
Uh it was a natural transition.
Um we had, as Joe just mentioned, just
created Veteran Intelligence
Professionals for Sanity.
Uh people laugh at sanity, but there was
no sanity at all going on in Washington
at the beginning of 2003.
The press had already been completely
corrupted. No one could get a word in
edgewise.
So, we wrote our first memo on the
afternoon, actually, of Colin Powell's
performance at the UN Security Council,
February
>> I stop you there, Ray, for a second? I
think you skipped over something. If
it's not classified, I want to know what
it was that made you into a dissident.
What happened? What did you see at the
CIA that changed you? And then how did
you meet Bob Parry? How did you contact
him? I've never actually myself heard
this story.
Yeah, well, he contacted me after we had
published a whole bunch of stories,
myself and then VIPS.
Um
but you know, this business about me
becoming a dissident actually is the
agency that became a dissident. I mean,
>> [laughter]
>> we believe it or not, uh we were created
to tell the truth. Truman wanted some
little agency responsible only to him,
okay?
Career protection by him to tell him
which end was up. He didn't want the
Pentagon, he didn't want the State
Department messing around with us. He
knew what it was like. He wanted the
real deal. And for most of my career, I
was a Soviet analyst, okay? So, there
was a big premium on getting that one
right. And we got it up we got it right
for two-thirds of my career, and then
Bill Casey and Bobby Gates came in. Our
institution failed, but the people I
knew
uh got it right, and I got it right, and
luckily by a
strange fate, uh I was I was working
with Ron Ronald Reagan's President's
Daily Brief, one-on-one downtown
uh with his vice president, secretary of
state, secretary of defense, chairman of
the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and the
national security advisor. Those were
the people we briefed. We were a team.
We'd do three two or three of those a
day. Reagan usually slept in. We seldom
saw Reagan. But this is a big deal. Now,
those were the days when when Bob was
searching around for making Consortium
News even better than it had already
been, and uh with the sanity that we
introduced here, it was a natural that
he asked several of us to uh sign up and
and write.
Um
I don't want to take a lot of time here,
but I was thinking about a vignette that
I could that I could tell a true story
about Bob.
Yeah, maybe I'll pick this one. Um
after Bob Bob had had made a lot of big
name for himself. I think he had a Polk
Polk Award, and it was just really it
was a big deal having disclosed Ollie
North's role, for example, in uh
in in the Iran-Contra affair. Well, he
was at AP at the time, but now Newsweek
wanted him, okay? Newsweek, okay? So, he
was promised certain things. Came down
to Washington. Started to have trouble
getting his stuff out, you know? But
about 6 weeks after he came,
uh he got word from his
director there in the in the Newsweek
office, "Oh, corp- a corporate's coming
down. Corporate. Uh
Maynard Parker. They're coming down from
New York, and they're going to have a
small
dinner. Can you come, Bob?" And Bob go,
"Yeah, of course I can." So, there was a
small dinner. About 12 of them, like the
12 apostles, you know? Visualize it,
okay? There's a a young
representative from Wyoming,
funny guy, his name was Cheney, okay?
And all kinds of really big what my
grandmother would call muckety-mucks,
all right, out of the table. And Bob was
there. Bob is usually not impressed by
this, but he's looking around, and
Maynard Parker's right at his at at his
left hand. So, in the midst of this
dinner, or at the beginning of it, um
uh Brent Scowcroft, who had just
left his post as national security
advisor,
uh piped up gratuitously and said,
"Well, gentlemen," and they were all
gentlemen. "Gentlemen, you know, uh
my successor, Admiral Poindexter, is is
going to
have to go to the Hill on Tuesday, and
uh he's going to testify about
Iran-Contra and what what we told the
president, of course.
I've told him that uh they should say
that we never told Ronald Reagan zero.
We never told him a thing."
Now, Robert Parry was not used to that
kind of milieu.
And unintentionally
he opened his mouth and dropped his fork
which shattered the
shrimp cocktail dish, made a big din,
and without thinking Robert Perry says,
"Joe Scowcroft, do I understand that you
would encourage your successor to
perjure himself before he testifies
before Congress?"
Yeah, that's how quiet it was.
Bob says
half a minute probably. Maybe it was a
minute. And then finally Maynard Parker
from Newsweek, CEO, big guy, he puts his
arm around Bob and he says, "Now, Bob."
>> [laughter]
>> Bob, you have to understand.
We know what's best for the people.
And there was chuckling.
Uh guess how long Bob stayed at
Newsweek.
>> [laughter]
>> I forget exactly. It was like four or
five weeks. They wouldn't So
the
the lesson here is simply
um
we know what's best for the American
people.
And if we have to lie before Congress,
come on, that's what you do. Why?
Because we can't let the American people
decide these things. Who
Who knows best? We know best. And Dick
Cheney and
Scowcroft and all of them being there. I
mean, that was a lesson for me. Bob
didn't like to tell that story very
much, but it's my favorite story.
And I have lots of others, but again,
I'm sensitive to how many others are
waiting in line here. So um
maybe I'll just say one other thing, and
that is that
when Bob died
Yeah, I'll I'll tell this little thing.
Uh I went to visit him at Arlington
Hospital.
Uh he had a stroke.
He wrote something after his first
stroke.
He was sort of compos mentis, but not
much, [clears throat] not really. And uh
I went in the room and and there were a
couple of people there and I I said,
"Hi, Bob." He looked at me, "Ray."
It's too much. It's just too much.
Too much. Yeah.
Right? Is that right? It's just I
I told you it's too much. So he he was
not really
he was not really with it completely,
but his message was that he knows what
brought him to this state. It was too
much.
And uh
and all I'm I'm only going to say here
is that yeah, it was pancreatic cancer.
But these things, you know, when it's
too much, when you have the kind of
stress
that Bob was undergoing with all his
friends, not all, not Sy Hersh, not
those kinds of folks, not us, but all
his old journalist friends abandoning
him and calling him a
calling him a conspiracy theorist
because he supported Gary Webb up till
the end. Um it was hard for him and uh
and that was was hard to see that he
kind of realized in a semi-conscious way
that yeah, it was too much. A lesson for
the rest of us. It gets to be too much,
okay? So uh
>> [laughter]
>> I think I've asked Joe Lauria to listen
to this little sermon, but don't let it
get too much for you. I think it did for
Bob.
We need you around. What's that?
He already is.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, but you got to
Yeah, but you got to deal with it in a
more sensible Bob was working
Well, he didn't accept calls on Sunday
morning because he liked to reserve that
for his grandchildren, right? Otherwise,
you know, seven days a week whatever the
hour uh it was urgent because we were
the only well, not the only, but for a
long time we were almost the only act in
town. And I'll just say that Joe, I'm
delighted to have you replace him
because you're carrying on the tradition
in a way that I never would have thought
possible. So thanks. Well.
Thank you, Ray. I Recording in progress.
I immediately made him a um
I already made a What am I saying? I
already made a within the first week or
two of taking over I made a change. And
that was that um
there's no working on the weekends. So
Bob worked seven days a week.
Now I only work four hours a day on
Saturdays and Sundays. So that's that's
Let's uh let's move. I want to ask you
some more about what Bob taught you and
uh some some of the highlights of
Consortium. So let's move on to John
Kiriakou who's been listening.
John, I don't know if your story is any
in any way How is it different from
Ray's story? You're both out of the out
of the agency and you both moved into
journalism and you're both writing for
Consortium News. Uh
but what's different?
Um what's different for me was that I
came around much later, I think, than uh
than Ray did.
Um
I I never met Bob Perry until 2015.
And I'm I had already been out of the
agency for 11 years at that point. But I
was just freshly out of prison.
And um
I was invited to a dinner at uh
at um
uh Barbara Capell's house in Washington.
In fact, you may have been there, Joe. I
I can't remember. You're at a lot of
them.
And
>> one of them. Yeah, so I met him at one
of
Yep, and Bob was there and we were
talking, just sitting at the table, and
about halfway into the evening he said,
"Wait a minute. Are you John
the torture whistleblower?"
And I said, "I am."
And uh and he said, "I'm sorry I I
didn't put two and two together." And we
chuckled over it.
And then a couple days later
a check arrives in the mail for $200
from from Bob saying he just feels so
bad about about, you know, the struggle
when you first come out of prison and
trying to make ends meet and and he
invited me to start to start writing for
the website. And and I did immediately.
And that's how I got to know him. Very
sweet man, very kind man, humble,
and um
and generous.
And so uh you know, honestly, my only
regret was I wasn't able to know him
longer because it wasn't too long after
that that uh that he had a stroke and
got sick.
And then that was the end of it for him.
But I was honored to know him even
though it was just a short period of
time.
Is that how you began writing ever
publication?
Was it Consortium News or even Yeah.
I I had known him. Well, I had been
I had been writing on and off for Reader
Supported News, which Mark Ash had had
created.
But it was
it was
much more of a mainstream
publication, even though it sort of
presents itself as
something more independent. I found it
to be, and this is not a criticism of of
Mark Ash. This is just an observation of
John Kiriakou. I found Reader Supported
News to be much more DNC oriented than
uh than I was
comfortable with over the long term.
And so I was writing for Mark, and then
I was writing for Mark and Bob, and then
I was writing just for Bob.
And that's
that that did me well.
But tell me what That's an interesting
point you raised. What is uh
how do you see Consortium's significance
in terms of the non-partisanship?
I mean, it's very easy I have for us to
be non-partisan cuz we we disagree and
dislike both major parties and we
criticize both of them equally. Exactly.
Exactly. Exactly. Listen.
You have never and Bob had never ever
told me
what to write, what not to write, what
position to take or to not take.
And at Reader Supported News, as soon as
Donald Trump won the Republican
nomination in 2016
uh we just were not allowed to criticize
Hillary Clinton. It was off the table.
No criticism.
It was anything to stop Trump.
And I said, "But Hillary's just as
corrupt as Trump is. Hillary's positions
on the issues are just as bad as Trump's
are."
And I said, "I'm not a Democrat. I don't
know why I should have to write in
support of of the Democratic nominee
when I don't like her and I don't trust
her."
And so it got to the point where he
said, "Well, I think we're not really
going to be able to use your articles
anymore." And I said, "Yeah, I'm really
not comfortable writing for you
anymore."
And then that was the end of it in 2016.
And that was now That was nine years
ago. Nine years have passed. I speak
with him every once in a while. All he
does is complain about Donald Trump,
which is fine, but that doesn't mean you
have to jump in bed with the other guy.
And so, you know, we just kind of wished
each other well, and that was the end of
it. It's bigger than that, John,
obviously. Bigger than that.
It's bigger than that cuz the mainstream
media, the newspapers, and especially
the main cable news, they're completely
partisan now. I mean, I blame
Rupert Murdoch for this because with Fox
News uh became the first one was openly
pro Republican one party. There was no
pretense anymore of objectivity. And
they blew the other MSNBC and CNN out of
the water. They destroyed them. So
eventually the other two networks had to
replicate that and they chose the
Democratic Party. So now these two all
those stream networks are ruined and
we've seen now that the mainstream
papers and Ray is very familiar with
this cuz he closely as Bob Day
criticized the Washington Post and the
New York Times almost every day about
the way they covered various things,
whether that be Ukraine, Russia, Russia
gate, Syria, etc. So So to how much
bigger is this problem about the
mainstream media? That's a good segue
after you and to Mary about the
mainstream media and what's wrong with
it from your perspective?
John.
Well, I'll answer that by by
telling you a a short anecdote. I used
to have a radio show with Brian Becker.
And
we covered a lot of politics on this
show. It was on the Sputnik network.
And so I would get up early every day
and watch Morning Joe on MSNBC because
they talked about politics more than the
other two shows. I normally flip around
through all of the networks just to see
you have to see what everybody's saying.
It's gotten to the point where Morning
Joe is unwatchable.
It's not about politics anymore. It's
just about It's just about hating on
Donald Trump and loving on whomever the
Democrats happen to have, you know,
leading them at any given moment.
Unwatchable because
for example, you know, and it is not
just MSNBC. It's It's CNN and Fox, too.
Unwatchable because everything the
Israelis do is is fine. Everything the
Palestinians do is a crime.
The Palestinians take hostages. The
Israelis take prisoners. That kind of
thing.
It's gotten to the point where none of
them are watchable. They're all biased.
They're all mainstream and they think
they're so independent of one another.
Um
that I I I'm at the point where now I'll
get the headlines from BBC.
I still read everything.
But
I get my Middle East news from a variety
of of Middle Eastern outlets,
both Israeli and and Arab. And um
and I can't rely on anybody. You know,
time time was, Joe, where I would say,
"Oh, I'll
I'll look to see what so-and-so is
saying. That'll give me a a good
overview of, you know, what the issue
is." I can't do that anymore.
I can't really look at the post anymore.
I mean, I read the post. I read the
times. I read the LA Times. I read the
journal.
But I skip all of the editorial pages
because I just simply don't trust any of
them. They're all biased
and they think they're so
they're so independent.
It's just laughable.
Now, in fact, I'll call them up. Now I I
start with, of course, the times, the
post, the journal. But then I have to go
to
the Guardian, the Evening Standard, BBC,
AP, Dropsite News, Al Jazeera, Al
Monitor, Electronic Intifada,
Consortium, Real Clear Politics, Axios,
etc. Covert Action Magazine. That's the
only way to really know what's going on.
You can't trust these clowns in the
mainstream. They're just simply not
intellectually honest.
Mary Kostakidis is smiling and nodding
and Mary, of course, was 20 years a face
of evening news and anchorwoman for the
SBS newscast and she transitioned into
independent journalism where she is now.
So Mary, take it from where John was
saying. What is the What is going on
with the mainstream media and what about
independent media? Is it really
challenging it today?
Okay. Well, from a former clown in the
mainstream media,
very good phrase.
Can I just firstly congratulate you,
Joe, and your team
on the work of Consortium News. It's
been invaluable to me as I'm sure it has
been to people around the world for a
very long time. And just to say what an
honor it is for me to join you here
today
to celebrate Robert Perry's legacy
with John and Ray and Patrick, whose
work I've admired
for years.
I think we live in dangerous times
because
of the unprecedented suppression of
speech throughout Western democracies.
Now, no one is suing the mainstream
media
because it doesn't undermine the
narrative sanctioned by the
establishment. So, however, the Gaza
genocide, I think, has exposed like
never before the failure of the
mainstream media to inform the public
and to provide analysis and perspective
that isn't profoundly disconnected from
the reality of the public seeing on
their devices.
So it's a continuation of the
dehumanization
of the people on one side of the
conflict, which has been happening for
decades and has resulted in impunity for
Israel and led to the genocide. They
still won't use the G word and nor in
Australia, certainly, refer to Palestine
[sighs]
because it's contested.
Though most countries in the world have
recognized it because Israel still has
to be treated with enormous tact and
respect. It's independent media that is
debunking the lies, providing context
and history and giving the other side a
voice. You know, most Australians will
never have heard anything Putin has ever
said, let alone Lavrov.
They are part of this sort of axis of
evil. You know, people and countries who
do terrible things because unlike
us, unlike our allies, they can never be
trusted. They're inherently bad faith
actors and that maintains a fixed
prejudice and polarization,
often based on ignorance, and eliminates
any chance of understanding a conflict,
let alone how it might be resolved.
You only have to look at the holy grail.
Objectivity, tick. Then we get to
impartiality,
neutrality,
balance and it's getting worse and worse
as you go. But they don't stick to it
anyway and this is why it's impossible
for many journalists to remain in the
mainstream media. Public trust in the
mainstream media started gradually
eroding
since the digital world enabled
connectivity for citizens. But the
genocide, I think, has amplified that
because of the profound moral injury of
those watching on their devices
compounded by the failure of the
mainstream media to hold governments to
account and the consequent failure of
leaders to take action that would stop
the genocide.
I'll stop there because I don't want to
talk for too long. All right. Let me ask
you one more question then. Um
You
You in the era in which you were on
mainstream television, there had already
been a consolidation of media in Western
countries. So we already saw
how corporate-run media was pushing an
agenda that was good for the interest of
powerful people and government. But was
there in those days, and Patrick will
weigh in on this, too, when we bring him
on.
And what were there in those days and
John Pilger used to always say that.
There used to be a space in the
mainstream media for someone like him.
For someone like John Pilger who would
plaster get his stories plastered on the
front page of the Daily Mirror in
London. Who made those incredible
documentaries for for Granada TV. And he
He said it's impossible today. He would
never, had he been starting today, never
been able to go into journalism or in
certainly mainstream journalism. So I
want to see if you did you recognize in
those days something that's gone and why
is it gone? Why do you think
it disappeared?
It is gone for for some of the reasons
you've been others have been talking
about so far. But to give an example,
the organization that I worked for was a
public broadcaster and I was part of
establishing the service. And we hoped,
those of us that were there at the time,
that we would be able to use something
other than
purely the global north lens to look at
the world.
And
and in the beginning there was an
attempt to do that. We would run longer
background stories on our news items in
the news.
But as time progressed and other things
happened in society and this is all
linked to other things. It's not Media
is not operating in a vacuum.
Uh we there was an influx of journalists
from commercial
television and
there was a
push to commercialize the public
broadcaster to have advertisements on.
So I was given an undertaking
because I was fronting the news my news
bulletin at the time that look, this
will never
impinge on the news. We will never cut
into news to run ads. Uh of course, that
didn't that that that's not what
happened. They They did precisely that.
And once you do that,
you start measuring eyeballs per 15
seconds, really. What sort of stories
are going to attract
more viewers. And that that the pressure
is on for you to do stories, in fact,
than that all the commercial networks
are doing. So, it fundamentally changes
the basis on which
decisions are made and it it it it
prevents you from fulfilling your
charter in fact. Um so, all those things
I think brought a sameness to what
people do.
Um there's validation, which is really
important. We'd all sit around and watch
other
other what other people were doing and
if if you're all doing the same thing,
then everyone pats themselves on the
back because you must have got it right.
You must have got it right because
you're not you know,
you you you're now in the big boys
league, you know, that there's the there
was that as well.
And at the same time as that, you had
this um you know, in addition to
looking at it through the same lens,
that sort of a global north lens,
uh there was also
there were other influences, if you
like. Inappropriate ones in my view. So,
take for example, the junkets, the trips
back and forth to Israel.
Uh which most journalists did
did. Um
and I'm not saying that they were all
affected by
but a good number would have been.
So,
uh
when they were here, they were wined and
dined by the Israel lobby. The Israel
lobby has a whole bunch of organizations
set up. So, you have this
large number of people with business
cards, letterheads, positions, CEO,
board director.
You know, they wear suits. They the
doors are open to them. They have access
to the top echelons of the media. Um we
can see how that happened with the
sacking of a journalist uh here
recently, Antoinette Lattouf. Um
a media campaign uh
lobby campaign was conducted where they
complained to the chair of the
organization. Now, the Palestinians
don't have that kind of access.
You know, so the the the the
power is skewed. Uh so, a whole lot of
factors converged on why I think we have
this situation. But, what it's resulted
in is that people have
um lost trust. And and I think um it's a
good thing for independent outfits like
Consortium News because more and more
people are turning to it. And I think
social media has been incredibly
important because that's the platform on
which you spruik what you're doing. You
say, "Hey, here and and that that that's
been my role to an extent. Uh the way
I've seen it is to be able to promote uh
perspectives that are not available on
mainstream media. And it's not just
journalists who uh
can no longer work on mainstream media.
It's a whole bunch of scholars and
experts and analysts. Uh you know,
people like Mearsheimer, Jeffrey Sachs.
I don't know. I I don't think he appears
they appear in American mainstream media
anymore and they certainly don't appear
uh in Australia.
Um so,
I think, you know, uh social media has
enabled uh the public to
to get it to see that there is this
other universe. Uh and that if they
don't engage with it,
they're left with really what is what we
call in Australia fish and chips
wrapping. I don't know if you use the
same metaphor, uh but that's that's
about all you can do with them the
newspaper. Wrap the fish with it, yes.
They used to be
when I used to eat the fish and chips
out of Daily Telegraph in London in
those days.
Uh Patrick Lawrence, Patrick is a former
Asia editor of the International Herald
Tribune. He has a long background in
mainstream journalism as a couple of us
on this
panel do. He's also editor of a book
called Journalists and Their Shadows, an
excellent book that I
was very honored to write the blurb for
a blurb for. Patrick joins us. He's a
also columnist for Consortium News and
various other publications like Sheer
Post. Patrick, you want to bring take up
the discussion, the state of mainstream
media. It's a big subject with a little
time, but if you can, give us your
insights.
Yeah, quite large, Joe.
I want to begin where Mary began uh
and to say how delighted I am to be here
uh not only among this
wonderful company but on the occasion of
the 30th. I I met Bob only once, right?
Uh and I'm I'm just very pleased to have
joined his organization.
Uh when you when you took over, right?
Uh
and uh
uh
well,
you've done wonderful things with it,
right? Uh and I think when Bob passed
away,
Consortium could have gone
any number of different ways, uh
up or down was were possibilities
and uh
here we are, you know, uh
it's wonderful to be part of this,
anyway.
Um
Now,
uh
in independent media, mainstream media,
uh I was interested to um
hear what uh John had to say
about reading mainstream media, right?
Uh
um
it's uh the credibility of mainstream
media
is
I think I don't think collapsed is too
strong a term, if you
uh
that's uh
empirical, but if you want statistical
evidence, all the surveys, Gallup and
Pew,
nobody believes it anymore. My favorite
stats are um
I guess they're a couple of years old,
but never mind that.
Uh
who was it? Pew, I think, or Gallup.
Uh what percentage of Americans believe
what they read in the mainstream press?
Take a sec.
16%.
It gets better when we go to television
and broadcast.
11% of people
of Americans believe what they
hear or see
>> [snorts]
>> uh in broadcast media, okay? So, but you
know, uh my other half is always
on me for spending too much time with
the New York Times. But, uh as I try to
explain, you don't go to the Times or or
any of its pilot fish to understand what
happened. You go to the Times to
understand what you're supposed to think
happened and then you're prepared to go
and find out what happened. Uh and and
this is the function of independent
media
in my view, right? It uh
Now, uh
uh someone mentioned Pilger.
Uh you know, uh and and my experience uh
John and I talked about this any number
of times. And the point is made in that
little book you mentioned. Um
Uh there was a place
for the independent
principled
journalist
um
uh for a very long time.
Uh
uh
And I think Bob was remarkably early,
listening to your opening presentation,
remarkably early and wonderfully harsh
in his assessment of what you could do
with it inside the tent, so to speak, uh
and what was no longer possible, right?
Uh
Uh and John and I agreed, there were
such places, not many.
Um and at a certain point, the medium
became the message. Um
Uh and I think things tipped over
uh
quite decisively in 2001, right? Uh
What happened in 2001?
Uh go back to the early Cold War years,
when the media were
uh enlisted
uh let me put that actively, enlisted
themselves uh in the Cold War cause,
right? Uh um
the same thing happened in 2001,
okay? I I think in
uh I think post-Cold War, there were
there was a kind of opening for a good
journalism for a while. I was still
doing it myself, right? Uh
Um
But I think after 2001
the imperium went on the defensive.
Uh and it was all hands
on deck, right? You you had to
uh you had to join the cause just as you
had in '47, '48, '49 and
and so forth, right? Uh
And I I think this is
pushed independent media forward.
Uh a couple of points about our
circumstances.
Uh our responsibilities
are far greater than our resources.
Uh that doesn't mean our
responsibilities
uh uh are are in any way to be
dismissed. They they are quite real.
Um uh as a number of us have said, you
you cannot understand what's going on in
the world without independent media at
this point.
Um
Uh
But [clears throat] we have
we have uh we have assets and we have
liabilities and uh I'll mention a couple
of the latter, right? Well, no. Uh
First I I think the
the best of independent media now
comes from
those of us who have had experience and
training
>> [clears throat]
>> in
mainstream media
because there's a question of standards,
right? Uh
Technical standards, okay? Not
intellectual standards, but how to do
things, right? Uh
>> [clears throat]
>> Um
Uh but
what Caitlin Johnstone made a point
about this just just this morning or
yesterday.
The reputation of mainstream media is
completely shot.
But what's going on now? Uh
the
our vote our vulnerability
is that we're digital.
Uh and you know, the whole sort of
algorithm story and all that, right? Uh
That was Caitlin's point. So, our
strength is our our also our
vulnerability,
right? Um
Uh there are other things I I would like
to mention.
They came up
when [clears throat] you and I met in
Switzerland uh this past summer. We need
a revenue model, you know? Uh Uh not
just because I'd like to be paid more.
That's a separate
topic.
But because we need to attract people
inside mainstream media. Uh
There are any you countless
reporters and editors
who would like to do better.
Uh you know, uh
I don't think they're all [__] right?
Uh Uh I think they're stuck with school
bills and all that sort of thing. Uh Uh
and we need a revenue model so that we
can grow. This is a long-term point,
okay? Uh
Uh figuring out how to um
attract
a good solid
trained journalists, right?
Where do you want to go from here, Joe?
>> [clears throat]
>> You're muted.
It warned that if you mute yourself, you
often forget and I just did. Um that's a
very good point you did about the
technical sides of the
Those of us in the mainstream, we
learned how to evaluate evidence, how to
gather news, what to to write the story.
I mean, these are things that not
everybody could just do it. I mean, no,
there's been a craze of citizen
journalism, but uh that takes away from
those of us who've actually worked in
this business uh for a long time and how
difficult it is. So, to combine those
skills and that experience with the
right political point of view is the is
the issue here because in the
mainstream, they can get the story, but
they they have they're skewed by
corporate and
uh government empire uh agendas. I
learned at the Wall Street Journal it
was very clear that they were pushing
American
foreign policy interests in their
reporting. They could not understand to
be
neutral, to actually independent
international [clears throat]
crisis is are extremely dramatic. If you
look at all as a play, different actors
in there. Take the Iranians, the
Americans, the Israelis. What's going on
on the battlefield there and to look at
them objectively and just describe
what's happening. It's a great story.
You don't have to push what the US
position is and to downplay the Iranian
position, the Palestinian position,
North Korean position. That also for the
our audiences dehumanizes these people.
It makes it easier to go to war against
them because our readers and viewers
don't have any kind of relationship with
average people in Palestine or in North
Korea or um
any other country the US is targeting,
Venezuela. We don't know these people.
So, you they're just statistics when
they're killed.
Right? So, this is a real problem, the
agenda of the mainstream media. And the
problem for independent media is we have
a lot of people who don't have those
skills that you're talking about,
Patrick. But if you know in the
mainstream who want to get out, I mean,
we were looking for people who can help
and the main independent media needs
these people. And I think that as all
three of us here were inside the
mainstream, tell me you and Mary and
myself, we were trapped inside. At least
I felt that way. I had a job. I had to
get a job. I didn't want to work for the
Wall Street Journal, God's sake. But um
Consortium News saved
uh the situation and it's a very rare
situation to have a publication like
this to work for. But there are people
stuck and trapped who want to get out
and do independent media.
>> Lots and lots. Um I want to uh I wanted
to mention um
how I've always been impressed with
Bob's
guts
uh in turning his back on the mainstream
at not only as uh you know, as
decisively, but as early as he did. Uh
And if I may take a moment, I want to
mention something Ray
noted earlier, right? Uh
Bob spent a few weeks at
uh Newsweek.
There's no publication better for
propelling anyone out of the mainstream
media, right? Uh And I I was quite
amused that uh
Maynard Parker uh it is the one who
seems to have passively persuaded Bob
get out of here, right? Cuz Maynard
Parker fired me in um
What was it? 1985?
Uh
It was a disaster. I was living in Hong
Kong with very high overheads, but one
of the great blessings of my career,
right?
>> [laughter]
>> Anyway, Ray, thanks for mentioning that
story. I liked it.
That's very interesting. That connection
there. I I want to point out that Bob
that Bob was ahead of the game in a lot
of other ways. Consortium News
went live on November 15, 1995 and that
was 5 days before November 20, 1995 when
salon.com
published its first online edition.
Salonmag.com it was called. That's where
Patrick was working and published the
very first Russia Gate story, the one
that we I referenced in my beginning and
and uh Ray pointed out. And then the New
York Times launched theirs on their
online edition January 22, 1996.
So, that was a a little more than a
month after Consortium News. LA Times
April 8, '96 and the Wall Street Journal
April 29, '96 and the Washington Post
June '96. So, it was all in that period
where the major news were going online
to try to get uh
get into this new medium of the internet
and Bob beat all of them. Cathy Vogans
waiting patiently and Sydney Cathy, you
have any put your camera on and if you
have any questions for our guest,
please.
Hi everybody. I'm absolutely fascinated
to hear your stories because back in
those days, I was an academic and until
uh at which point I you know, I became
aware of what WikiLeaks was uh
reporting. Um
Mary, can you can you talk to me about
how dangerous it became back then
to actually make news cuz I started
becoming an anonymous citizen journalist
back then. But tell me about how
dangerous it was for your professional
reputation to be associated with an
organization which was basically being
called a a terrorist organization and
Julian Assange was being called a
high-tech terrorist.
Well, I was out of mainstream media by
then, Cathy.
Um I think it would have been very
difficult for me if I'd still been
uh in the thick of it.
But um
it was certainly
certainly um
it puts you outside the circle.
You know, uh
because they did such a good job of
smearing his reputation.
Um
uh that anyone who supported him or I
mean I I thought having met him
after I met him, I thought, "Wow,
he is smart. He's clever.
He's well informed. He understands
geopolitics
better than all the journalists in the
newsroom I'd worked with put together.
What does that say? You know, it blew my
mind.
Uh so and I thought they don't get it.
They just don't get it.
So he became a real threat and then
listening to stories um
of how, you know, the whole thing began.
I mean, he was just, you know,
someone with a backpack and everything
in his backpack and Mark Davis at the
time was a journalist. He was following
what he was what what Julian was doing
and he convinced him that he needed a
couple of interns to help him manage
this process and he was there in the
bunker with the
New York Times and the Guardian and
which was the other publication?
Um Le Monde? No. Well, there were Yeah,
there were various German uh anyway. Der
Spiegel. Der Spiegel.
Der Spiegel. Yes. Yeah. Uh
and um
you know, he was they they all had
PPEs and and he was this sort of
colonial um
and uh so I think they thought, you
know,
just hand it over, little boy. You know,
that kind of attitude.
So um
anyone who was associated with him or
was uh stood up
it wasn't just a matter of standing up
for him, although they did terrible
things to him personally. Um
He he deprived He was deprived of his
freedom.
The I don't know how he dealt with being
confined in a space for so many years
and not being able to go outside. You
know, the
the impact is beyond my comprehension.
Um
but
it wasn't just about him. It was about
press freedom and it's about the the
very core of journalism, getting to the
truth. Getting to the truth.
And and going back to some of the other
things everyone else has said, it is not
about
whether you're left or right.
What's happening today is people on the
left and right. I mean, I listen now to
what Charlie Cook was saying towards the
end and I think, "Yes. Yes."
And I listen to Tucker Carlson. I mean,
I I take my hat off to him because he
has the capacity to change his mind. How
many people in the mainstream media have
demonstrated that?
You know, so
but then I'm accused of being a
conspiracy theorist because and they
talk about this horseshoe. I don't know
if you've come across the metaphor. I
hadn't before where the the loopy left
converges with the loopy right. You
know, so we're all conspiracy theorists
and uh
So um
but
we're we're finding resonance amongst
the public and that's what matters. When
I when I appear,
you know, when I talk
to at events, I sense that the public is
with us.
They aren't with them. I mean, of
course, you know, being on social media,
I get trolled badly. I get sent bombs. I
um you know, people are rude to me.
Go back to where I come from and all
sorts of
things far worse than that and it's all
water off a duck's back, um frankly.
But essentially, I think there's been a
massive impact by
independent media, independent
journalists
uh and that we have to
uh
capitalize on that and and going back to
your point, Joe, work out a way of
making this
feasible,
workable financially because that's the
problem at the moment. And I have just
to finish quickly, I have to tell you
I was highly amused the first time I saw
it because I was unfamiliar with the
with the model, really, but I
I've watched um Judge Nap do it and I
think I've watched Tucker do it where
you do an ad in the middle of, you know,
what you're doing. All of a sudden, you
pop up and talk about gold or
>> [laughter]
>> investing in gold or and
it's just blew my mind, you know, cuz
it's it's um
isolated
and and and and then it goes back to
what was happening and
I think it's based on the fact that the
people advertising are doing it because
you have
a certain number of listeners. I it
doesn't
I don't think
it doesn't work in the same way as as
the mainstream media where there there's
pressure for you to do more of the
stories and adopt a position that's
going to bring in more money.
Because this that decision rests with
that individual.
It rests with Judge Nap and Judge Nap
makes it very clear what he wants to
achieve in the same way that you do,
Joe, and and everyone associated with
mainstream media. Sorry, uh Patrick, did
you want to say something? No, wait. I
have to I have to do the spot on copper.
I'm selling copper.
No. Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> I was I was going to say Mary I do want
you to go to the front page of
Consortium News and click on the donate
button and send us your coppers. Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> I was going to
Mary, I was going to say it's
it's either gold or nutritional
supplements. Don't forget those.
>> Yes.
>> [laughter]
>> And may I interrupt for a second? Mary,
I'm
embarrassed
I'm embarrassed to even say that uh
that I'm beginning my gold and
nutritional supplements pitch on Tuesday
for my [laughter] podcast.
I want to mention something pertinent to
what Mary
said, okay? Uh
When I I was away for a long time in
Asia,
um
various periods
in total, 29 years.
But when I was coming back for the final
time in 2010,
uh I I sensed immediately
that uh this has to do with
public
what the public what readers want to
see. I I sensed immediately that uh
post-Iraq invasion and all that,
people were quite eager,
as I said, eager on the way to desperate
for a new
story.
Not only
a new rendering of what happened in Iraq
or
what was happening in Syria or
whatever, right? But a new version of
uh
a new version of
uh what America was doing, the West by
extension,
um
uh
uh stripped of myth and all that,
um and and I think
to understand independent media
it in its largest
uh context,
uh
we're presenting a a new version of
historical reality, right? Uh
uh not only Ukraine or Gaza or what
whatever story you wish to name,
but uh
a kind of
new idea of
the West,
of the United States, and uh
what it's doing in the world, and let us
not forget, Joe will agree with this,
the history of it. How we got here,
right? Uh historical context.
Uh lies by omission are
very powerful. Uh
and one of the great omissions of our
time is the historical context. Uh
Ready-to-hand example of
so obvious it's a bit simplistic.
The world the history of
Palestine-Israel
we're supposed to think began on October
7th.
It's It's just too obvious to dwell
upon. But uh
that goes on always always always.
Here's another one. Uh
The the history of the Ukraine crisis
began
on February 24th or 22nd, whatever it
was.
February 24th, 2022. That's when the
crisis began.
Not in uh
1991 when the West began to betray
uh Moscow
uh with the collapse of the Soviet
Union. We all We in this room all know
that history. It's omitted, right? And
this is what independent media are
doing. Not just that story, that story.
Uh
a new I I don't like this word, but I'll
use it. A new narrative of
you know, a
a new contemporary history, right? I'll
stop there.
Uh Ray, can I get you to weigh in on how
indepen- independent media actually won.
Now, going back to the Assange case, one
of the key strategies that we employed,
and Mary, you will uh um
you will agree with this. So, is that
well, we started giving all kinds of
academic bodies, intelligence bodies
started giving awards for accurate
reporting. We have the Sydney Peace
Medal
that was awarded to Julian Assange
indicating that this was a pathway to
peace, accurate information. And uh Ray
McGovern, we have the Sam Adams Award,
which you attended, and people like
Thomas Finger, who was reporting
accurately on um
weapons of mass destruction apparently
in uh Iran not not true. And then Julian
Assange got
behind that.
Julian Assange also won that Sam Adams
Award.
Uh
can you can you give us an idea of how
step-by-step
even though we didn't have the primary
audience immediately, which we we do
now. You have to just look at the stats.
Not just in terms of credibility, but in
terms of actual viewers who prefer
independent media as transmitted via
social media. How did How did that
happen? And And why did it work?
Well, thanks, Kathy. Um yes, these are
good questions.
You had to have met Julian
for long enough
to admire him to the point where you
would do anything to secure his freedom
and to spread his message.
First time I met him was in the anteroom
there of the uh place there in the
Ecuadorian Embassy in London. Uh we were
celebrating a Sam Adams Award for a very
different kind of person. He was the
head of State Department intelligence,
but he had stood firm
and prevented Bush and Cheney from
making war on Iran because he said in a
national intelligence estimate Iran had
stopped working on a nuclear weapon at
the end of 2003,
had not returned or not resumed. So,
that's the one major NIE, National
Intelligence Estimate, that I know of
that played a huge role in preventing
what Bush and Cheney, by their own
admission, read their memoirs, had
intended on their last last year out.
So, here here we are in the anteroom.
We're drinking wine Julian comes in from
his quarters there, and he And I'm next
to him. And I said, "Uh
Julian."
"Yes." "I'm Ray McGovern."
"I KNOW."
"OH."
"You read MY STUFF?"
"NO."
"I SEE you on YouTube."
Lesson.
Teaching point there.
Julian was no spring chicken. I think he
was 39 or 40 at the time, but he already
knew that if you're going to going to
reach the younger generation, you can
write really fancy things, and I do, and
I'm hopeful I'm really happy that Joe
publishes But, you know, you got to be
seen to be heard, so to speak. So, that
was my first Well, then we gave Julian
the award.
And then we gave um a uh
Chelsea Manning the award. And we gave
Daniel Ellsberg the award 2 years ago.
It was a very moving ceremony because he
he duly was celebrated for for his first
leaks, which helped put an end to the
Vietnam War in 1968,
not 1975.
So,
so the the the notion here is that we
have uh Craig Murray, and we have Annie
Machon. We have people from Britain. We
have uh a Dane major uh that
spilled the beans on Poul Rasmussen uh
they're lying about. So, we have an
international group here. We're on our
25th, I believe, nominee right now.
But, the idea is
solidarity, okay? Mutual support. People
get recognized by people they admire for
doing what is for doing what is good,
okay? So, um last thing here on this
thing
is that uh in the Catholic Worker House
in Baltimore, where uh Phil Berrigan
used to be a part, there's a great big
sign behind the common eating area, and
it says, "The first duty of discipleship
is to support one another."
Solidarity.
Well,
now I recommend that
to all of us because And we should be
together next year at this time, Joe.
This is very salutary. It lifts my
spirit. It's just good to be with the
rest of you guys. I have a little bit
more to say about that, but I don't want
to monopolize the conversation. Maybe I
could back later.
Yes, Mary.
Sorry. Go ahead, Joe.
No, go ahead, Kathy. Uh okay. So, Mary,
I I just wanted to get back to this
um concept of how we actually achieved
predominance uh in the independent
media. I think it's something to do with
news for everybody, and that goes back
to what you said, Joe, about ordinary
people. They want news, but it has to
talk about them. So, did we Did we
actually get there through projects like
Unity for J,
where uh you know, there were
there were the 50 people in at a time
talking uh all about the same subject,
also congregating on one single issue.
Uh the whole idea
being that okay, we can come together on
one single issue. We don't have to agree
on everything. Is that kind of the way
that that
an audience was finally gathered?
I think people come to it um gradually
for different reasons, but I think
it's more that
the other side stuffs up and stuffs up
badly. Um and and I think going back to
what Ray said about the importance of
visual impact, um this is what Julian
did with with collateral murder. It was
showing that tape. I mean, there was a
whole lot more in the revelations, but
that tape was emblematic of what was
happening, and and it spoke to people.
Uh and in the same way, when Madeleine
Albright is asked, uh was it worth
killing half a million kids, and she can
say, "Yes, I think it was worth it."
Uh that's shocking, but
it do- hasn't had the same impact as
watching children
beheaded, shredded, half their faces
blown off, their intestines hanging out.
So, we are at a moment where the public,
I think, in much larger numbers have
gone, "Whoa, there's something very
wrong here.
There's something
I knew I couldn't trust this media, but
now I know I can't trust it. And the the
the the problem is because uh no one's
been able to stop this slaughter,
um
people are thinking, "Well, hang on, but
what What does it mean? Not just for
these people who are dying, these
children are being killed.
>> [sighs]
>> What does it mean for us? For our
future? For our children? Because if no
one's prepared to stop someone doing
this, they can they'll do it to someone
else next."
Yes. Yes, exactly.
>> I think it's a That's why I think this
is such an important moment in history.
Uh not just in the in the the
geopolitical sense, but in in terms of
the media uh and and um
and the and uh independent journalism
and uh
you know, our capacity to tell people
different for people to come to
independent journalism for uh what they
think is more likely to be the truth.
Yes. Uh look, Patrick Lawrence has got
something to say here. I I would just
interject uh as well. I'm not not
exactly interject, but to say that
we we are in a crisis of the collapse of
international law. And uh you know,
there are a lot of people that are not
getting justice, and
you know, I think he has to say
something about this fundamental
problem.
Um, go ahead, Patrick.
Yeah, I
this [clears throat] actually more a
question than anything else, okay? Uh,
Ray mentioned the necessity of
being seen.
Uh, and everyone in this room
understands the drift toward podcasts
such as we're doing right now, okay? Uh,
but
>> [clears throat]
>> you know, uh, I taught journalism for a
number of years in Hong Kong and
elsewhere.
>> [clears throat]
>> And I used to say to my students, look,
you go off on an assignment or something
and you have all the gadgets you can
possibly dream of,
but
I have never found
uh, an electronic gadget
or technology that replaces
reading
and language
for thorough authentic understanding.
You just mentioned international law and
all that. I I I I don't know how you
would get that on a camera, right? Uh, I
don't want to sound like some sort of
stickler,
but we My point is we have to analyze,
and maybe this is a professional
question, not of so much interest to
listeners or viewers at large. We have
to analyze what balance we need between
podcast, visual impact, everyone knows
the impact of film and video,
and print in order to if what My point
earlier was we are
interesting phrase
making history. That was my point
earlier.
We are not just reporting Ukraine in a
different way, right? Or any other
story. We are producing a new version of
history.
Uh, and how do we do that? I don't think
we can leave language behind.
Uh,
all by way of a question. I'd love to
hear others' thoughts.
Yeah, uh, so
John Kiriakou, or Mary, go ahead. No,
no, no, I just was wanted to agree
wholeheartedly with what um,
Patrick has just said. And and of
course,
Patrick is a a master
of the English language and and an
absolute joy to read. So, you know,
every piece is incredibly moving.
Um,
and so, I I agree with you. You have to
have a combination uh, because uh,
different uh,
mediums will
will
will appeal appeal to different
audiences. Um,
but also, I think it's more potent when
you can offer, as Consortium News does,
as Consortium News does, a combination
of those things.
Well,
Mary, uh, we Excuse me, cut you moment.
We have constantly discussing this
balance between our print and video. We
are a print publication going back to
'95. Bob Parry began some videos.
Uh, he knew it was important. Uh, we
have built this up, but the demands of
the print the the the the labor It's
much more labor intensive to produce a
written article, I have found. Many
times I wake up in the morning, I want
to do a commentary, I make notes. I
never get to write it. Now, if I did a
short 20-minute video presentation, I
could probably do bullet points and
discuss what's on my mind. So, we
definitely want to move more to that
type of video. We have a great producer,
executive producer over there at City
Lights, Robin. She's extremely
uh, talented and and professional, and
we are not making enough use of her. So,
uh, we're going to do more video that,
but we're not going to as Patrick
saying, we're not going to sacrifice
the core of what Consortium News is,
which is the written word, which, you
know, that's what I That's my
background, so
uh,
anyway, I I think it's a really good
point. You And also, I want to also echo
what Patrick said about historical
context. That's I think the essence of
Consortium News is
to provide what the mainstream leaves
out, and that is historical context.
Once you take out whatever happened
before October 7th, the story changes
completely.
It's like we opening a novel in the
middle and you see a woman shoot
someone. Well, why? What happened before
that? We don't know. Mhm. So, we're
saying, "What did he kill that guy?" So,
Putin on a He's a He's He woke up one
morning, he decided, "I'm going to
invade Ukraine." No reason. We don't
have any reasons given to the public.
He's just a madman. He's Hitler. This is
the Sudetenland. This is He's going to
march on all of Europe. And they're
making so much out of that, European
leaders and the press, that he that he's
planning on conquering all of Western
Europe. Now, they say
Ursula von der Leyen on the one hand
says that they use machine uh, washing
machine parts
the for the Russian tanks.
But on the That's on the one hand. On
the second hand, they're going to be in
Russia will be in Paris by Christmas.
So, which one is it? Are they a threat
to Western Europe, or are they so
bumbling that they have to use machine
washing machine parts for the So, it's a
complete lie. And once you leave out the
what happened before the coup in '20 You
go back to '91, you can certainly go
back to 2014, where the civil war began
that Russia intervened in. That's gone
from the consciousness of the Western
audience, never mentioned, and that is
so crucial. Of course, that's the same
story with
uh, Israel-Palestine. You got to go back
to '48, and that has never been told,
that story. We have the Exodus Leon Uris
version rattling around in most
Americans' and Westerners' and
Australians' and Europeans' heads that
eliminates and excises and air brushes
out
the out of the history
the
most important story that
doesn't mean you're taking the side of
Russia or Palestine. You're just telling
the story anyway. That's my
my bit there.
I just wanted to hear from John
Kiriakou. Um, so, at the moment, I mean,
it it's realized uh, how important
mainstream media is, but you have people
like Larry Ellison um,
and buying up all of the major platforms
uh,
what can we do, you know, given that
TikTok is going to be
um,
censored or moderated um,
in a way that favors this dominant
voice? Because this is essentially what
it is. It's a battle for the ear of the
the ordinary person who who wants to
hear news that concerns them.
It's about a platform that inspires
empathy
when you see people suffering on the
other side of the world. This was never
done before. What can What can
independent media do if our platforms
are going to be taken over?
And it's going to but hopefully not
revert back to how it was before.
Well, let me make a couple of points be
before I offer up a
what's probably a weak solution, but
it's the only one I can think of.
Um,
like Joe,
I
I default to the written word. I
I have a a lot of trouble.
Listen, I I have a
a standard insult
that I like to that I like to give every
once in a while, that any slob can roll
out of bed and make a YouTube video.
Right? You live in your parents'
basement, you wake up in the morning,
you roll out of bed, you eat some
Doritos, and then you put on a news show
on YouTube.
So, I I I just can't. I can't watch
videos. I can only read things like what
we produce on Consortium News.
But with that said, what I've done is
very carefully over the years, I've I've
sort of um,
I've sort of What's the word
that I that I should use here?
I I've
I've very carefully chosen
those news writers whom I know I can
trust.
People like Patrick and Ray and Mary and
and you, Joe. Our colleagues at
Consortium.
Um,
a dozen and a half others. And and I've
tailored my
Twitter feed, my X feed, just right.
So, now I find myself getting most of my
news from from my X or from Blue Sky or
wherever people happen to be publishing
where I know that I can find them and
they're not going to be censored.
And I've taken some criticism from
friends for this because of Elon Musk
and all, but so long as the people whose
judgment I trust
are able to publish on these platforms,
I'll seek them out on those platforms.
And so, that's what I've been doing.
Yeah. Ray, you've
got a huge audience on Judge Nap for the
Intelligence Roundtable.
But is the mainstream going to take over
the narrative again?
Well, it won't take it over from
Consortium News or from Judge Nap's
program.
Uh, the question and and I My view is a
technical one, how how powerfully they
can shut us down, how powerfully they
can
physically eliminate us. Let's say that
doesn't happen anytime soon.
Well,
I think there's a synergy here.
Uh, I think there's a uh,
John has heard me say this many times.
You know, I think that in terms of
breaking into
the consciousness of most Americans.
The fault is
The fault is not in our stars, but in
ourselves.
Now, that's too harsh. On the face of it
is too harsh.
But aren't we smart enough?
I'm not smart enough, but don't we have
enough grandchildren and children that
are smart enough
to figure out a way
to get us before more before more
Americans.
I have to think
there's some sort of way to do that. But
I've been saying that for 20 years now.
And uh for the nonce, I think it's just
terrific that we have Consortium News
and Consortium News Live.
And so we just have to keep plugging
around and not plugging away and not uh
later.
Uh I want to get back to Bob Parry.
He He was such a a important influence
in my life.
Truly. Uh
a model. Not only how to write how to be
a journalist,
but how to be a person, how to be a
mensch, okay?
Cared about people.
Uh when he was going off to Salvador,
uh
he gathered his children
and said, uh
I just want to say I'm leaving tomorrow
morning
and I'm going to a very war-torn torn
place. I want you to know that and I may
not be coming back.
Uh Nat Parry, his youngest son, wrote
this. He said, "Well,
I was young and I said, 'Daddy, why
don't you Why can't you just stay here
with our family?'"
And Dad said, "Because children are
being killed."
And Nat,
"It You mean children like us?"
And Bob Parry, "Yes, children
just like you, okay?"
Now, thank God he came back.
And what he uh launched as people talked
about 1996,
19 1996 was a big year. The year after
it was founded, that the year after.
Well, that's when Gary That's when um
Gary Webb published his book about CIA
facilitating
um crack cocaine in the United States
through the contras.
Bob Bob had been with that story.
He had been turned down, of course, for
reasons we all know. But when Gary Webb
published that well-researched story,
who was the first guy to support Gary
Webb? It was It was Bob, okay?
And Bob did everything he possibly could
to support him and failed. Gary Webb, as
you probably know,
committed suicide having lost his
profession, couldn't find a job, and
lost his family at the age of 49.
Now,
Bob talked about this and
uh Nat noted it in one of his articles.
I just want to share with you what Nat
said.
Um
Bob's conclusion, of course, that the
Reagan-Bush administration had colluded
with drug traffickers to find the to
fund the illegal war in Nicaragua. Bob
could prove that and Gary Webb had
proven it. Now,
sadly, the damage done to Gary Webb was
done.
Um
Here's what Bob said on Democracy Now
when Gary Webb committed suicide, quote,
"There is a special pain.
I think all of us have felt this pain.
There's a special pain when your
colleagues in your profession turn on
you,
especially when you've done something
that they should admire and should
understand.
To do all that work and then have the
New York Times and the Washington Post
and the Los Angeles Times attack you and
destroy your life,
there's a special pain in that."
Now,
let me just share just a little bit of
my special pain. I used to
work with a guy, let's call him Dick.
We did the President's Daily Brief
together, okay? He was a really smart
guy, but he couldn't He couldn't go out
of the Democratic consensus when it came
to Russiagate.
So, here he says uh and fluently
in in 2017,
publicly, "I have had to denounce Ray
McGovern for his adulation for Putin,
whose virtues exist solely in Ray's
imagination.
The NATO extension that he and I warned
against was not a casus belli for
Putin's invasion of of the Ukraine, blah
blah." So, I wrote to him and said,
"Dick, you know, you know better. You
got to apologize to me." And he wrote
back, and this is the telling thing.
"I will not apologize for denouncing the
sharp turn in your thinking. Ray, you
are manifestly wrong and your effects
are evil. I have to conclude that
something physical or psychological
happened to you.
And now [laughter] I feel myself
relieved
that I no longer have to fear
that I would be investigated
for having been associated with you."
Wow. Mhm. Quits.
Mine quits. Mhm. Now, this is a This is
a really educated guy, been around a
senior officer there. And this is 2017.
I I've written him a couple times since,
but even in view of the the latest
deluge of proof that Consortium News and
Bob Parry and Joe and Joe was right on
this, too. Joe got criticized by what
was that the
the uh
NewsGot?
No, no, the HuffPost HuffPost. HuffPost
did a job on you, yeah. Yeah, we won't
go into that, but I I I could couldn't
believe that they'd do that to Joe, so I
I sent expressed a little solidarity to
him. So, I guess my little message is
there's a lot of pain in this. And one
way to assuage that pain is to get
together. And again, we ought to do this
every year, if not every month, okay?
And just the notion of looking at your
guys and knowing who you are and what
you stand for and what the guts you have
shown, John Kiriakou, almost 2 years in
jail. I visited John in jail. It was not
a pleasant place, okay? And he got there
because of John Brennan. John Brennan is
going to be held accountable now, we all
hope. So, you know, there's lots to do
and I'm, you know, able to do it still
and I'm really happy that I am and I'm
glad that we have Consortium News Live,
we have Consortium News, and we have
this great group of colleagues.
Brennan, of course, um involved in
Russiagate with Comey.
And that was intelligence agencies
interfering in domestic US politics. And
that is the essence of Russiagate. I
think that's the problem. It's not a
par- partisan thing.
Certainly nobody at Consortium News ever
supported Donald Trump, starting from
Bob Parry. And up to me and everybody
we've ever published.
We're not supporters of Donald Trump at
all, particularly the second term.
But the idea that intelligence agencies
would interfere in the politics, even to
try to stop someone as odious as that
guy is wrong. And that's why I said in
my introduction, there are some people
who are just driven by self-interest and
there are others who are not driven by
self-interest. But the people who are
can't conceive that anyone would be
motivated by anything other
than self-interest because it doesn't
help us to write what we do cuz we're
going to get smeared as pro-Saddam,
pro-Putin,
etc., etc.
Et cetera. James Comey is is the example
par excellence here. Uh
personal interests.
He said in his book, and you've heard me
say this several times, Joe,
uh when people say, "Why
People asking, how could you possibly
take such liberties with the law, with
the regulations, with the whole
schmear?" And he wrote in his book,
"I was operating in an environment in
which Hillary Rodham Clinton was sure to
be the next president of the United
States." Period. End quote. And I would
quote that all the time. Look, that's
why. Can you understand that why? And
now we know from his handwritten notes
that he was ready to Yeah, I'm I'm
planning to serve in the in the Clinton
administration. I bet he hoped hoped to
be Attorney General or something. So,
that's how vain, how irresponsible, and
how people think they can get away with
these things and so far have.
I hope they're held to account.
Patrick.
Yeah, I I wanted Ray Ray Ray McGovern
just touched on a really interesting
point about Russiagate, okay? Uh
Russiagate was structured in 2016
precisely on the
understanding, universally held, not
even Trump thought he was going to win,
right? That Hillary would be elected on
November 8th of that year.
So, it's a
uh
uh I uh
I go to the metaphor of design
tolerances, okay? Uh
An M1 tank has rather considerable
design tolerances. It's supposed to last
who who knows how many years, right? In
very adverse circumstances. It The
plastic toy under your
Christmas tree for your 6-year-old son
is supposed to last about 4 hours,
right?
>> [laughter]
>> And um
And Russia gate was supposed to last
just until November 8th. And on November
8th 9th, it would fall apart. Nobody
would give a [__] right? Uh
And it didn't. Um
and so the the Democrats were stuck
with trying to make
uh trying
They were they
put themselves in a position to make a
machine with very fragile design
tolerances last 4 years. And that's why
the mess of Russia gate became so
preposterous.
That's my theory.
You You should write an article about
that for uh
for of our
>> Just in time for Christmas, under the
tree. [laughter]
For the nation. Try to write an article,
Patrick, for the nation on that.
Well, I've got one final That's a GREAT
IDEA.
>> [laughter]
>> I'VE GOT one final comment and it sort
of relates to their finding in them over
there, so we don't have to fight them
here.
People like Mary Kostakidis
are plowing through this horrendous
primary evidence
of
war crimes, crimes against humanity,
genocide, so that a lot of the others um
don't have to do it.
But um I'd like you to
tell me what that's like, Mary, and then
I'd like to pass it on to Elizabeth
because she's been waiting patiently to
ask questions of all of you guys. Thank
you.
Mary, you're muted.
I think she's thinking. She's not muted.
>> [laughter]
>> No. Um I was saying I'm I'm not sure
whether your question is trying is uh
aimed at
ex- getting me to talk about my case,
which I, you know, I don't think I I
don't particularly
um
want to do only because this
conversation is about uh
a much broader and and more important
issues
uh than that the the price that an
individual
um who's, you know, privileged and my my
um
uh uh life is not at stake. I'm not in
jail. I'm not paying the price that that
John has paid or Julian have paid. Uh
and um and my grandchildren are safe.
But Ray, I I've loved every story you've
told. And the one about
uh the grandchildren, they've all rung a
bell for me. But the one about the
grandchildren, I had a similar
experience where I was My grandchildren
were born in the US. They're US
citizens. I've spent a lot of time in
the US because of them.
Um but they've come to Australia now.
And uh
trying to explain to them what is
happening in the Middle East in a way
that um
at their age they can understand. I
mean, they're about eight, you know,
eight and 12, nine and 10. Oh god. Um
uh that age group, you know, between
eight and 12, nine and 12. And um
And I also don't want to say anything to
poison their
um
love and and notion of what the US is.
They They love the US. That's where they
were born.
And so when in talking about the war, um
the war
uh it's not a war, the genocide, and I
do use that term when I speak to them,
um my grandson said,
"Just tell me one thing.
Are they killing children?"
And I said, "Yes, they are." And he put
his hands in his pockets and walked off.
And he said, "I don't want to I don't
need to know any more."
Mhm.
Um and I think you're right, Ray. It is
those It is that
we can't afford to lose
you know, our being in touch with our
humanity. And
for those of us for whom that is the
most important thing. I mean, I'm I'm
asked, "Well, you know, what basis are
you doing all this? You know,
posting what you are on on X.
Are you a journalist or, you know, what
are you doing?" And And
Well, yes. Yes, I'm a journalist. But
primarily, first and foremost, we're all
human beings. And whilst the principles
that you apply in your journalism
are integral to who you are anyway,
um
you you can't divorce that. You can't
You can't separate it. And I think the
issues that we are discussing as
journalists, the public are entitled to
discuss as well. So it's not
it's not something that we can argue
that we have ownership of.
We have an obligation to
um
to
uh
communicate in a way that it you know,
that has
all those principles of journalism
at the fore of our minds. But the
humanity
uh
is is is is integral integrally related
to that. You can't separate it.
It's my view. Thank you, Mary.
Elizabeth.
Thanks, Kathy. Um I was thinking as you
were all speaking and as I was kind of
considering what we heard in the
introduction about the way that Bob
Parry founded Consortium News in
response to that censorship within
uh corporate media. How is since that
time, how is censorship changed, you
know, during this whole internet age and
independent news media kind of growing
up but being throttled within this age
by censorship? How do you see that
changing now? Things like AI coming to
the picture.
Uh and how does independent media
survive despite all of the censorship
that seems to just grow year by year?
The You Who are you asking, Elizabeth? I
missed. Oh, me. Oh oh oh oh. Sorry, I'm
going to have to ask you to repeat it so
I can concentrate more.
>> [laughter]
>> Sure. So obviously, Consortium News was
founded in response to censorship. So
how has censorship changed, you know,
especially in the last few years? Where
are we going forward? How How does
independent media survive moving
forward? Not just financially, but in
terms of the censorship apparatus that
keeps changing. Well, the censorship's
an enormous problem. And um the fact
that uh material is being disappeared is
an enormous problem. And I think Kathy
understands understood that very well
when her uh account Twitter account was
discontinued.
Uh and now, of course, with
um
the policies that are being implemented
by various corporate entities who we
have given control to over saving our uh
the the material that we create, whether
it's our documents on our computer or
uh videos that we create.
And
um
that is an enormous challenge. I I I
don't know the answer to that. And
that's probably the subject of a of a
a different panel dis- a panel where we
can have the input of people who um are
perhaps like Julian, who has who has
been thinking about these things for a
very long time. Um
but
it is an enormous challenge because
the it's not only interference with
algorithms that will amplify
um certain
uh narratives and and diminish those
that, you know, don't con- that they
don't like. It's about
disappearing you completely. And so if I
were were taken off
uh X now, I would lose an enormous
amount of work uh and evidence and
access to evidence that um that I need.
Uh and I I I
I don't know what the answer to that is.
I wish I did.
I think I think Patrick had some
thoughts.
Would you like to add something?
Elizabeth,
it's a wonderful question
precisely because there's no answer just
now, right? But what makes it a good
question is it shoves us up against
the reality of
independent media, right? Uh
I'll betray my age a little bit. I I
started working in non-mainstream media
parallel to my
published career
way back during the Vietnam
war days, right? Uh for a paper called
the Guardian, not the British Guardian,
the American Guardian, okay?
There was
uh
I'm not sure how much censorship there
was then. There was infiltration. You
never knew how many people in your
newsroom were FBI, that sort of thing,
right? Uh
>> [snorts]
>> But it's digitized now.
Um
and we exist because we're
digital.
Our projection, uh
look what we're doing just this moment,
right? Uh
But uh I I made this point earlier, not
to repeat.
Our
our great strength, projection and so
forth,
is also our burden, and I don't know uh
uh I'm with Mary. Um
I don't think there's an answer, but I
think it's extremely important that we
contemplate this question, right? Uh uh
uh
Max Blumenthal addressed this some some
long while ago and said, "We do it until
we're not able to do it anymore, right?
Uh
uh That's not bad for an interim
solution, you know? Uh
But uh I think we have to come to terms
with
the
the the
the universe of digital media, very
complicated.
Uh it's sort of on the one hand good, on
the one hand very we're, you know,
I think I've made my point, though.
I'll leave it there, and maybe others
have thoughts.
Thanks for the question, I suppose, is
my point.
Ray, did you have anything to add or
I think what Elizabeth is raising is the
question of the backlash. Now, we've
seen
independent online media starting with
Consortium News in 1995, and look at
where we are today. Um
On the right and on the left, Grayzone,
for example, on the left. Drop Site
News, which has done incredible
reporting about the Epstein story right
now, in terms of the actual high-level
contacts, diplomacy that uh that uh
Jeffrey Epstein was performing for the
Israeli government. Deals with Mongolia,
deals with Elizabeth, what are the other
countries there? Mongolia, uh
uh
trying to make a deal with Russia.
>> Russia, Syria. He was meeting meeting
with Putin. Sorry. If we can believe
>> Yes. these emails, he met with Putin,
and he set up tried to set up
He was a liaison between Israel and
other governments.
We had on our show this various show, CN
Live,
Ari Ben Menashe, a former Israeli
defense intelligence agent, who said on
our show twice and over a couple of
years now, that he that Jeffrey Epstein
worked for Israeli intelligence. Of
course, people didn't believe him. A lot
of people didn't believe him. Well, now
we know it's true. But where is that
reporting in the mainstream from the
Drop Site News?
We see online or we see these
influences, a word I I despise, but I
don't think we're going to get away from
it.
Well, I don't know what an influencer
Well, they're online. They're social
media personalities.
People on the right who have million
more than a million
followers on Twitter, millions
[clears throat] of people. What more
than CNN's nightly shows are garnering
right now. They have larger audiences
than CNN or MSNBC.
And they are they were invited a bunch
of, by the way, to Israel. I did a story
on that a few months ago to teach them
what they're supposed to say about
Israel.
So, the Israelis are not stupid. They
know where it at. They're not They don't
care so much about CNN anymore. They
care about these young influencers with
2 million and more of viewers. This is
part of the independent media landscape
they were going in. And the judge The
judge has come up. I wonder and I've met
the judge several times, and I keep
forgetting to ask him.
Um and I could just write him an email.
Did he
when he started this thing, Judging
Freedom, did he think he'd have a half a
million subscribers
within a couple of years? Maybe he did.
But that is an extraordinary amount of
of viewers, half a million people. So,
what is happening is that the mainstream
realizes they're losing this ground to
to likes of us and all these other
people I'm mentioning, and there's a
backlash. And that backlash we've seen
now with the government is the Twitter
files, where the FBI and Homeland
Security actually told Twitter take down
people's tweets.
We have seen uh the Terrorism Act in
Britain being used to arrest and
interrogate British journalists as they
return to their country,
including Richard Medhurst being held
for 24 hours, simply because of what
they're writing or saying about Gaza.
We have our on on a small potatoes
thing, Consortium News now. If you want
to put one of our articles on Facebook
right now, you're going to get a
forbidden 403 message.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Any idea why that happens?
We don't know how to resolve this. We
don't know who to talk to.
So,
there's a big backlash against
independent media because it's winning.
And mainstream is going down the tubes,
and all their careers, their
multi-million dollar salaries at the big
networks, they see what's going on. And
I think there's a this is part of the
backlash, the way to use algorithms to
crush right and left center independent
media, which has exploded, and they
don't know what to do about it. I'm
sorry, Patrick. I'm done.
Yeah, uh Joe, uh
you you inspire a thought or two
in response to Elizabeth's question,
right? Uh
Maybe there's more of a
Maybe there's more of an answer there
than uh Mary and I thought, right? Uh
It goes to the question of
fragmentation.
Okay? Uh
You mentioned the Grayzone.
Uh
There are other things.
Uh MintPress. I think Consortium.
They're too big. Max is too big
[clears throat]
to wipe out, cancel, whatever your word
is, okay? Um
uh I
I wasn't uh
uh
on a couple of a different occasions uh
because I'm not very big, okay? But the
problem I think we we come up against
the question of fragmentation.
Substack's all over the place. Um
uh and um
what I'd like to see in uh
in independent media is a degree. It's
It's not a very welcome word in many
contexts, but I'd like to see some
measure of concentration,
so that the independent media who are
really carrying the that are really
carrying the banner uh uh are large
enough
and strong enough and visible enough, so
they can't be
they can't be wiped out.
That's that's just my thought, maybe uh
I'm kind of in a mode of making
statements and calling them questions,
but uh
that's you know,
that's what I think.
Uh too much fragmentation
in independent media. Uh And Blumenthal,
yeah.
He's a
superb journalist, right?
I.F. Stone said long, long ago,
uh
"Every generation has
a handful
of authentic journalists."
Uh
I think Max is
one of them in his generation.
Uh and they're not going to be able to
remove him.
Not to personalize it with Blumenthal.
MintPress and others,
uh Alan MacLeod, you know,
they can't do to these people
what they have done to others.
Myself or other minor example.
You still have the floor, Elizabeth.
If you have any more questions.
I don't think I do at this moment. Okay.
subbing part of it. I feel that was a
really great statement by Patrick, and
I'm kind of floored by it, so I'm still
taking that in. Thank you.
Yeah, I think we're at a crucial point
here, and this is an important
point about whether independent media
survives
if whether mainstream media survives. Um
but I don't see how I can consolidate
this um
Oi.
What do you think, Mary? Is that Mary
who piped up?
>> Well, um Yeah.
Uh
a situation arose in Australia recently
where
um we tried to have impact as
independent journalists, and we realized
that we don't really have a voice, not a
collective voice. And we considered
and it's still on the cards that we need
to form some sort of association
uh
that allows us to remain independent,
but allows us to come together on
certain issues.
Uh
For example, in
>> A consortium. That's your missing word.
>> Yeah, exactly. [laughter] Exactly, a
consortium.
That's exactly right. Um
Because when when there are discussions
about journalism, and there was one that
that was quite dangerous, in my view,
from which we were all excluded.
Um One was about, you know, press
freedom, and
Julian Assange was the elephant in the
room. And none of us were allowed to
participate because in case we, I
suppose, raised
that issue. Um
But um it it's of concern because, you
know, this is where the editors get
together and senior journalists, and
uh they contemplate issues like, "Oh,
should we have an informal D notice
um operate so that we talk to
in you know, the head of the Intel
services in Australia before we do a
story to get their point of view
on things.
That kind of thing. And and we don't
have a seat at that table.
And and so yes, to to your point, I
think we do need some sort of
coming together at particularly then to
to assist when one of us does get
attacked
and and that happens. And I I don't feel
as hopeful as you Patrick that people
who are very senior or who have
not very senior but who have large
followings won't be attacked because
from what I can see on X it's happening
to people with
large groups of followers and
people who I think you know, I may not
agree with them politically for example,
but it they have a right to say what
they're saying. And I agree with some of
the things they say. But
I don't I just don't
I can see it's very easy to make them
disappear. So
I think we have to I think we have to
really value what we have and try and
make sure that we find a way for it to
survive
in the long term.
I think Patrick's right about being too
big to fail like like Max Blumenthal and
somebody like Carlson
who has I don't know how many more than
a million I'm sure several million maybe
followers on X. He's an independent
journalist. He got kicked out, right? Of
mainstream. And he's picked up. He's
doing what we're doing but with an
enormous following. How could they
destroy him?
They could prevent us from posting stuff
on Facebook.
But I don't see how they can bring down
a really big Now Ray and I by the way
Yes, go on. I think you need to ask
Tucker that question. I was listening to
Judge Nap
once and was shocked by what he said and
it was a throwaway line. I can't
remember whether he was interviewing
Mearsheimer or who it was.
But he almost said to himself I've been
a friend of the president's for 40
years.
But I think they're going to come after
me.
Yeah, that was the judge who said that.
Yeah. Now John if you have something you
want to tell to Carlson
John's your man
cuz he's he's in touch with him. I'm
not. So uh
Yeah, I'll tell you he he genuinely is
worried
about this exactly this kind of thing. I
I know Judge Nap as well not as well of
course as Ray does.
But Judge Nap has been worried about
this
for
the last five years.
With Tucker it's it's new.
And and Tucker's not the only one. There
was a
a major and public break today between
Trump and Marjorie Taylor Green.
Marjorie Taylor Green this wackadoo who
all of a sudden I find myself agreeing
with 75% of the time on some of these
issues.
But their their break has been very
public. Trump today called her a traitor
and withdrew his political endorsement
of her.
So I mean who who knows what to make of
all this and where does it all end?
It's not like the courts we can count on
the courts to protect us anymore.
Oh, that's a very good point. Very good
point. I think you want to stay away
from
the courts so we have our own
experience. But you know, Ray and I were
at a dinner in Chicago at the end of
September just when you mentioned Mary
about associating and Patrick you're
talking about forming an association and
some organization called Integrity Media
with huge deep pockets that we didn't
know about put on this incredible dinner
at the University Club in off Michigan
Avenue and everyone that we know in
media with I turned around every I saw
somebody I turned around there's Kim
Iversen I turned around there's Jimmy
Dore I turned around there's Alexander
McCoy who sat at my table there's Ray
there there's Robert Scheer there's and
I on my table as well was uh
uh
from antiwar.com Scott Horton and on and
on and on everybody who's just about
anybody in our
world was at this dinner and I thought
this is incredible. And one thing that
bothered maybe Ray agrees I don't know
is that it was a little bit like it was
we were making celebrities out of the
people who were up there who won awards.
Aaron Mate was the
MC and awards were given out to Jimmy
Dore and to Robert Scheer.
And so we don't want to become
celebrities in that way. We've got to
avoid that kind of thing. But on the
other hand there was a feeling I don't
know if you agreed with it that those of
us
that we didn't realize that together we
had this kind of incredible community.
And that we were all in one room
together for one night. And there was a
feeling of strength there and
solidarity.
Well, I agree Joe and it goes back to my
point about solidarity.
Just knowing other people are out there
and in one room maybe 150 people there.
Most of them people like you and me. And
besides that we got a nice little cup
from the Unity
>> [laughter]
>> I have mine on the shelf right here.
That's right there.
But all kidding aside it was an
incredible night and that was the first
time they did that. It was funded
[snorts] by by this group that
does have a podcast that does support
please pull like well, Bob Scheer gets
some support from them and others. So
yeah, there would be good that there be
liaison between those people and the
rest of us.
You know, trying to
have a umbrella organization. I think
what Mary said about the initial attempt
in Australia is very instructive. It's
got to be done delicately. It can be
done and I think there are some benefits
to having some sort of
corporate sort of thing saying well, all
right.
Are we are we not giving this area of
the world enough attention? That kind of
thing. But uh
Yeah, there's a lot of us out there and
we need to be more open and supporting
one another.
With Judge Nap for example, I'm
[clears throat] always telling him let a
hundred flowers bloom. Let a hundred
flowers contend. Mao's expression.
Uh
There's
Where I grew up as an analyst in the CIA
you coordinated things, right? If Max
Blumenthal wanted to say something and I
wanted to say something and and
what's his name Alister Cook wanted to
say something well, we make we sort of
come to terms and then say it in a in a
in a cogent way but together.
That doesn't that doesn't totally work
and it's good this way because every all
our all our views disparate as they may
be get out in the public. Let me say one
other thing.
There are some certain things that
uh
I'll just give an example from my own
recent analysis.
There are some things that seem like
gems to me. McGovern you got that one,
you know?
And what I'm going to suggest is when
there's a gem in all of us many gems
there's got to be a
vehicle that brings that to the rest of
our attention. So we have to watch all
of all of shows of Judge Nap. Here's two
gems, okay?
Putin's not going to stop in Ukraine.
He's going to take Poland and then he'll
take the Baltic states. Okay? If you
think he's stopping Ukraine you're
crazy. Direct quote from President
Biden, okay?
Answer, Putin already stopped.
He stopped in April 2022
when he scared the hell out of Zelensky
and they had a deal.
That's when he stopped. So you prove to
me that he won't stop. He has already
stopped, okay?
That's the
perfect squelcher on that one. Number
two.
These geniuses
the West's policy now on Ukraine is the
following. See if you can
See if you can understand.
We're not giving any more money or arms
to the Ukrainians.
We're going to give weapons to the
Europeans.
When we get them we don't really have
enough right now but in a couple years
when we get them we're going to give
them to the Europeans. They're going to
pay us with money that they well they
don't really have right now but they'll
make it maybe get it. And then the
Europeans are going to give them to the
Ukrainians who will not at that point
have any soldiers or real armed forces
to man them. I mean it's a genius idea,
isn't it? It's stupid on its face and
when people say to you oh you think
Putin's going to stop? Well, that's one
thing. And if you think that you know,
we have a plan for you if that's the
plan for Ukraine. Well, I think little
correct me if I'm wrong and these may
not be gems at all. But these shorthand
little things if they're available to
all of us and we all have them. I mean
those are just two that I think I have.
If they would would be kind of
circulated in some
some bulletin board say hey, this week
this is what I thought. Feel free to use
it. I don't know. I'm just talking off
the top of my head, which is not very
good.
>> We're We're still, you know, as a
journalist, even as independent
journalists, there's a competitive part
of this business that you cannot deny.
So, there's always going to be some kind
of competition to get the story. I think
a little bit of that is good to motivate
people.
And I don't see how you could create an
organization
uh coordinate that, but um
you know, you said that you and um
Alice to Croc and others uh
in a sense, the judge asked you the
exact same question and the same day.
So,
you're getting getting all of your
answers coordinated in that way, even if
it's not intended like that.
Yeah, I think it's good the way it is.
Uh Yeah.
>> Yeah, I do, too.
I do.
>> Well, I I just like to mention the fact
that uh Jeremy Corbyn
at one point um
you know, during the worst moment for
Julian Assange, he called for all the
independent media channels to live
stream the same thing at the same time.
And and then we would we would outnumber
the the news going out from mainstream
media.
But I also just want to
um respond to what Mary said about my X
account being canceled, discontinued, I
think was the word she used. It has not.
Um I'm still on X, but I'm in solitary
confinement.
So, I can see the world, but they can't
see me.
Um
I have been
uh you know,
robbed of all my connections.
I've been
confined in in a way. I have nothing
more on my feed as well.
Um and
this was somewhat of an accident, I
believe. There were
five
over five I think it was 5.3 million
people this happened to in the first
half of 2024
alone. And a lot of these cases uh
in my case, there was no explanation
given.
A lot of these cases, there is a prove
you're human test
that I completed and X uh told me, "Yes,
congratulations, you've
proven you're human." But then it said
there was a problem in returning me to
my account.
And that resolved uh
2 weeks later into me being permanently
suspended with no particular reason.
This has happened to a lot of people,
and Mike Pence has really spoken out on
this because there's been a lot of
mom-and-pop businesses that have been
wiped out wiped out.
And also, people like myself that are
generating a lot of evidence, as you do,
Mary,
on X because we trust that platform.
Um that all of that has been removed
from the historical record.
It's an extraordinary thing, and they're
still charging, Kathy, by the way, every
month. Yes,
for a year.
For a year.
>> How many millions of people you said are
in that position?
>> 5.3 million in the first half of 2024
alone. I mean, this kind of thing
started with Alex Jones, and there was a
lot of people who said, "Yeah, get him
get him off
the net. Get him deep platformed." But
now this thing has been happening to so
many people, presumably accidentally. I
I had a [laughter] long conversation
with Grok,
uh X's AI, which I'm not allowed to talk
to anymore, but um in particular in
relation to the billing for premium
account. And And Grok said that that X's
monitoring algorithms are not talking to
their billing algorithms anymore. And if
you write to the address on your
invoices, the email address on your
invoices, and say, "Hey, will you stop
billing me while my account is broken?"
They tell you that this email account is
not is not
monitored anymore. So, you will not get
um a response.
I have had I have reported technical
faults on X
in the past, and I had a a fantastic
response, you know, people getting back
to me, someone signing his email Paul,
and then [clears throat] writing uh you
know, saying, "We're going to fix this."
And then writing follow-up emails to
say,
"Is it still broken or is it working
now?" And all that kind of thing. But
you can't get to an email box and uh uh
you know, a human, I should say.
And Grok agrees with me that any kind of
complaint, if you are canceled on X,
it's a dead letter box. There's
absolutely no one there. And that that
somewhat corresponds to
>> This was a long time ago. uh
discontinuing the employment of
thousands of people. Yeah, I was about
to say that, Kathy, that this was
supposed to end with Musk. This was a
Twitter problem before.
>> That every that so many people were
censored and and
cut out. Uh and then Musk it it turns
out that it's the conservative voices
that they wanted to preserve. They were
only upset
about conservatives being canceled. Like
um
Trump himself had his Twitter account
suspended, if you recall, while he was
still president.
So, it's unfortunately it's uh it's a
partisan issue that they will go after
each other's, and this is not getting
any better. But I think it's time for us
to call this evening to a close on a
happy note because all the misery that
we've experienced that we report about,
you know, uh we used to say at the UN um
that if there weren't any wars, how many
people go out of business? So, we are um
we are uh you know, we're going to put
that aside for a moment.
The absolute horror of Gaza, the the
incredible dangers of Ukraine and the
possibilities of a nuclear conflict,
these are all
These are all very serious matters that
are real. But I want to raise up a
bottle here
>> [laughter]
>> show us that we are going to celebrate
Consortium News's 30th birthday. We have
reason to feel good about what we've
accomplished. And not only us, but all
of independent media, as we've been
discussing, challenging a a corporate
and governmental monolithic power that
wants people to all think the same. And
we're still keeping alive diversity of
thought
and dissident. So, I'm going to try to
open this cork here online on
There it is.
You may have heard that, I don't know,
but uh-oh.
>> [laughter]
>> I have a glass, but I'm not sure I need
it. Okay, I'll get it. I'll get the
glass.
>> Well, everybody else have a glass there,
Kathy? Does it
>> this is this is an empty can that I
managed to find. Um
so, I'm going to I'm going to toast with
a Coopers Green, which is um
non-preservatives. It's It is a good
Australian beer. Um made in South
Australia. And uh
the reason that I want to toast with
Well, not really toast, cuz it's empty.
But the reason is because, you know,
United States has been our number one
audience on Consortium News. And in
2020,
uh
Australia, which had been number three
audience, moved to number two. And in
the last month, Australia is our number
one audience. So, hello, Australia.
>> [laughter]
>> We must be doing something right in
Australia. Cheers.
>> [gasps]
>> Cheers.
Ah.
Excellent. Well,
we will meet again. Maybe next on the
31st anniversary, Ray, if you want to
make this a yearly
tradition, we certainly will do that if
you anybody else wants to take part.
I thank you all. We lost Patrick, but
yes, Ray.
Yeah, Joe, you mentioned I have Stone as
uh
one of Bob Parry's patrons or
uh I just like to
recite a quote from him, very very
short. I know what it is, and it's
wonderful.
Yeah. I love this quote.
>> he was saying, "Look, if you're going to
do this investigative
journalism stuff, go in it go into that
with your eyes open, you know, because
you got to realize you're going to lose.
And then you're going to lose, and then
but then you're going to
lose again.
But then one fine day,
you might not be around,
but somebody who thinks, believes, and
is courageous like you is going to win.
Okay?
And so, in the meanwhile,
you realize all this, and you take it in
stride. You rejoice when it's time to
rejoice, like right now. And you
keep a perspective on this thing because
we're not supposed to be successful
always. We are supposed to be faithful.
And Joe, again, I hold my hat up for to
you for being faithful to the vision of
Consortium News, and for recruiting such
incredible people as Kathy and others to
help this this ship
go ahead. So,
uh I have Stone comes to mind. I think
he's right. We have to keep that balance
and take some joy in the interim.
What he was talking about Ray, and I
love that quote, is the definition of
sanity. You keep doing the same thing
over and over and over again, and one
time it's going TO WORK.
>> [laughter]
>> WELL.
NO, THAT WAS GEORGE BUSH.
SO, we're going to keep plugging at it
with Cathy, with Elizabeth, with our
Yeah. business manager Michelle
Steinberg, with our
deputy editor Corina Bernard, and all
the great columnists and writers like
John Kiriakou, As'ad AbuKhalil, Patrick
Lawrence, Ray McGovern,
and others.
Even we we just published a new piece
from Lee Camp, who was writing for us a
few years ago. He's back with Consortium
News. So, Good. we can't do it without
these people, and you know, it's a grind
putting out a daily publication. It's
really something. And then when it's all
done, the day is over, and then you
think, "Shit, I got to do it again
tomorrow." Same thing.
So, it is
having a background in daily newspapers
helps,
because you did you have the discipline
to do it.
But, you know,
we we are really grateful to our donors,
and we've got many people who have
sustained us over these years,
the eight years that I've been in
charge, and the many years before that
with Bob. And I want to thank all of
them right now, and I hope that you
continue to help us.
And it's to them that we have to produce
work every day, and they've come to a
lot of them have come to depend on us as
other independent media to get a
different point of view that we're being
force-fed from above. So, thanks again
Ray, Mary, John,
Cathy, Elizabeth, and Patrick for
joining us tonight on our 30th
anniversary celebration. Happy birthday,
Consortium News. Happy birthday,
Consortium News.
Birthday.
Get out your notebook.
>> [music]
>> If you are a consumer of independent
news, and the first place you should be
going to is Consortium News, and please
do try to support them when you can. It
doesn't have its articles behind a
paywall. It's free for everyone. It's
one of the best news sites out there,
and it's been in the business of
independent journalism, and adversarial
independent journalism for over two
decades. I hope that with the public's
continuing support of Consortium News,
it will continue for a very long time to
come. Thank you so much.
>> [music]
[music]